Guide to the Jonathan Edwards Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings of Jonathan Edwards, c. 1720-84; Series I; 10.3; (21 boxes)
  - SERMONS
    - CANT. 1:3: "That Jesus Christ is a person transcendently excellent and lovely" "Our Lord Jesus Christ is a most lovely person" (p. 2), 1733 Jun
      See: Box 13, folder 993
      "At Boston"
    - CANT. 2:3: "The true believer hath rest in Christ" (p. 3), 1733 May (Box 4, Folder 258)
    - CANT. 2:3: "Prop. I. There is this difference between Jesus Christ and all others that men are wont to trust in for salvation, that he is as a fruitful tree and they are barren ones" (p. 1), 1746 Apr (Box 4, Folder 259)
    - CANT. 2:16: "They that can say of Christ, 'My beloved is mine and I am his' have great reason humbly to glory in such a privilege" (p. 1), 1747/8 Feb (Box 4, Folder 260)
    - CANT. 4:8: "Christ calls and invites souls that are under the most dark and dismal circumstances to look to him" (p. 4), 1736/7 Jan (Box 4, Folder 261)
    - CANT. 5:1: "That persons need not and ought not to set any bounds to their spiritual and gracious appetites" (p. 3) (Box 4, Folder 262)
    - CANT. 5:3-6: "Tis a frequent thing that the saints miss of sweet communion with Christ for want of a little self- denial" (p. 6), 1737 Jul (Box 4, Folder 263)
    - CANT. 6:1: "When some are converted this should stir up others to be converted also" (p. 3), 1734 May (Box 4, Folder 264)
    - CANT. 6:10: First, I would shew how the saints are said to look forth as the morning I. They are lightsome... 1. They receive light... 2. They shine forth by reflecting the light (p. 1), 1741/2 Feb (Box 4, Folder 265)
    - CANT. 7:13: "Prop I. The precious fruits that are found in the saints are pleasant and entertaining to Jesus Christ Prop II. Tis much to be desired that there should be found in those that are godly gracious fruits of all sorts Prop III. Tis very desirable that there should be those exercises and fruits of grace in the souls of the saints that are new as well as old for the entertainment of Christ" (p. 5), three sermons, 1736 Sep (Box 4, Folder 266)
    - CANT. 8:1: "That the Incarnation of Jesus Christ was a thing greatly longed for by the church" (p. 4), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 267)
    - CANT. 8:7: "The love of true saints to Jesus Christ is such that nothing can extinguish or overcome [it]" (p. 1), 1746 Dec (Box 4, Folder 268)
    - IS. 1:2: "I shall discourse from the words at this time 1. by considering how we are the children of God 2. [how] God has nourished and brought us up as children 3. how heinous it is for such to rebel against God" (p. 2), 1746 Nov (Box 4, Folder 269)
      "Lecture to young people"
    - IS. 1:5: "There are some men that whatever means are used with them, will only grow worse and worse" (p. 4) (Box 4, Folder 270)
    - IS. 1:18-20: "That all God's methods of dealing with men are most reasonable" (p. 4), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 271)
    - IS. 3:1-2: "That it's a manifestation of God's displeasure against a people when he takes away from them many that have been useful and serviceable among them" (p. 2) (Box 4, Folder 272)
    - IS. 3:10: "That a good man is a happy man whatever his outward condition is" (p. 3)
      See: Box 13, folder 994
    - IS. 5:4: "That it may well be asked concerning some persons that are unprofitable under means of grace, what God could have done more to them that he has not done" (p. 5), 1734, 1757 (Box 4, Folder 273)
    - IS. 5:20: "That the putting of evil for good and good for evil in affairs of religion and the concerns of our souls is a thing of very fatal tendency" (p. 3) (Box 4, Folder 274)
    - IS. 6:3: "The subject: the holiness of God" (p. 1), 1747 Aug (Box 4, Folder 275)
    - IS. 6:3: "God is an infinitely holy [God]" (p. 1), 1753 Jan
      See: Box 13, folder 995
    - IS. 6:5: "There is nothing like seeing what God is, to make men sensible what they are" (p. 4), 1734 Jul (Box 4, Folder 276)
    - IS. 8:9-10: "If God be with a people whose destruction is sought by foreign enemies, how numerous soever those enemies, whatever their desires and... their designs...they are likely to be entirely confounded and broken in pieces" (p. 5), 1745, 1755 (Box 4, Folder 277)
      "Fast on occasion of the proclamation of war with the Indians Fast"
    - IS. 8:21-22: "When once wicked men come to be in absolute despair they will curse God" (p. 2), 1742 Sep (Box 4, Folder 278)
    - IS. 9:6: "Christ above all persons that ever did or will appear in the world is the most eminent Counsellor" (p. 1), 1749, 1752 (Box 4, Folder 279)
    - IS. 9:7: "God acts in the affair of man's redemption as one greatly engaged" (p. 1), 1747, 1753 (Box 4, Folder 280)
    - IS. 9:13-14: "When men are so regardless of divine chastisements and corrections as to continue unawakened and unreclaimed by them, it brings 'em into great danger of utter destruction" (p. 1), 1747 Aug (Box 4, Folder 281)
      "After Elisha Clark was killed"
    - IS. 12:6: "When God is in the midst of a people tis just cause of exceeding joy and praise in them, that so great and holy an One is amongst them" (p. 4), 1735 Nov (Box 4, Folder 282)
    - IS. 26:10-11: "The obstinacy of some wicked men is such that means won't win them nor will all the advantages enjoyed in God's visible church take any effect upon them nor will any of God's providential judgments or threatenings reclaim them" (p. 2), 1740 Sep (Box 4, Folder 283)
    - IS. 27:13: "What I design from these words is to shew how the preaching of the word may fully be compared to the blowing of a trumpet and especially as that was used among the Israelites of old, and then make some application" (p. 5), 1741 Jun (Box 4, Folder 284)
    - IS.28:16: "I. Christ is the foundation on which the church is built..." (p. 2), 1741 Dec (Box 4, Folder 285)
    - IS. 30:12-13: "There can be no safety for the children of men whatever their present circumstances may seem to be, as long as they go on in wickedness" (p. 5), 1748 Jan (Box 4, Folder 286)
      "Fast on occasion of the burning of the courthouse"
    - IS. 30:20-21: "One great end and design of God in appointing the gospel ministry is to shew his people which is the way of duty when they [ministers] see they mistake their way and to be a means of an increase of light in the church" (p. 4), 1749/50 Mar (Box 4, Folder 287)
    - IS. 30:30: "When God comes to execute deserved punishment on ungodly men, everything that they shall suffer shall be with great displays of the indignation and wrath of God" (p. 1), 1742 Mar (Box 4, Folder 288)
    - IS. 32:2: "I. That there is in Christ Jesus abundant foundation of peace and safety for those in fear and danger," three sermons, 1752, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 289)
    - IS. 32:17-18: "They that have true grace and work righteousness have a foundation for the most excellent and everlasting peace and quietness", 1750 Jun (Box 4, Folder 290)
    - IS. 33:14: "Wicked men cannot bear the misery of damnation" (p. 2), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 291)
    - IS. 33:14: "The time will come when fearfulness will surprise the sinners in Zion; because they will know, that they are going to be cast into a devouring fire, which they must suffer forever and ever, and which none can endure" (p. 5), 1740 Dec (Box 4, Folder 292)
      "Preached the parts marked in the margin at Stockbridge," preached to Stockbridge Indians
    - IS. 33:14: "The sinners congregation are in an eminent manner sinners in Zion. Now there is no great appearance of their being afraid... But the time will come when they will be afraid..." (p. 1), [ca. 1750-51?] (Box 4, Folder 293)
    - IS. 33:17: "They that are the true subjects and sincere and faithful servants of Jesus Christ shall be admitted to see their King in his beauty" (p. 5), 1736 Jun (Box 4, Folder 294)
    - IS. 33:19-24: "1. I would observe who they are to whom the promises in the text are made 2. Observe what promises are here made to such" (p. 2), 1746, 1756 (Box 4, Folder 295)
      "Fast Octob. 16, 1746 on occasion of the arrival of the French fleet"
    - IS. 35:8: "Those only that are holy are in the way to heaven" (p. 4), n.d.
      See: Box 13, folder 996
    - IS. 37:28-29: "1. I would observe what is here declared concerning the danger God's people were in in Hezekiah's time 2. What is here set forth concerning their deliverance" (p. 2), 1746 Nov 27 (Box 4, Folder 296)
      Thanksgiving "after the confusion of the French fleet that came to Jebucta[?]"
    - IS. 37:31: "The way in which God makes his church and people to flourish is by causing them to take root downward and bear fruit upward" (p. 3), 1746 Mar (Box 4, Folder 297)
    - IS. 38:18: "They that are gone to hell are all of them in despair" (p. 6), 1733/4, 1752 (Box 4, Folder 298)
    - IS. 40:29-31: "Obs. 1. Those that have the greatest strength have no strength of their own sufficient to carry 'em on in that way which God calls 'em to travel" (p. 6), 1741 Mar (Box 4, Folder 299)
      First booklet in series of three, contains Obs. 1-3
    - IS. 40:29-31: "Obs. 4. The degrees in which God gives strength and grace to those that wait upon him are very diverse" (p. 1), 1741 Mar (Box 4, Folder 300)
      Second booklet in series of three, contains Obs. 4-5
    - IS. 40:29-31: "Obs. 6...To wait on God in the improvement of what strength we have is the way to receive more and more strength" (p. 1), 1741 Mar (Box 4, Folder 301)
      Third booklet in series of three, contains Obs. 6-7
    - IS. 41:19: "In the future glorious times of the church of God in this world, the saints shall be like trees that are always green" (p. 1), 1742 Jun (Box 4, Folder 302)
    - IS. 44:3-4: "Observation: The pouring out of the Spirit after a long witholding of its influences is like the giving showers of rain after a great drought" (p. 2), 1749 Aug (Box 4, Folder 303)
      "Thanksgiving for rain"
    - IS. 44:3-5: "For I will pour water upon him that is thirsty..." Here is 1. a promise of what God would do 2. the happy consequence of it: (1) in the conversion and enlivening of multitudes, (2) the effect of converting grace upon them 3. When this should be..." (p. 1), 1741/2 Mar (Box 4, Folder 304)
    - IS. 45:25: "The people of Jesus Christ have great cause to glory in their Saviour" (p. 2), 1754, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 305)
    - IS. 47:3-4: "When God's time comes to take vengeance on his enemies he will not meet them as a man" (p. 2), 1749, 1753 (Box 4, Folder 306)
    - IS. 47:4: "I would first shew how Christ is the Lord of hosts and the Lord of armies, and then secondly shew what is implied in its being said that this is his name" (p. 2), 1743 Oct 13 (Box 4, Folder 307)
      "Thanksgiving for the King's preservation and victory at the River Maine in Germany"
    - IS. 51:8: "The work of redemption..."
      A series of 30 sermons in 12 booklets, published at Edinburgh, 1774, as A History of the Work of Redemption
      - No. 1, sermons 1-3, 1739 Mar (Box 4, Folder 308)
      - No. 2, sermons 4-9, 1739 (Box 4, Folder 309)
      - No. 3, sermons 10-11, 1739 Apr (Box 4, Folder 310)
      - No. 4, sermons 12-13, 1739 (Box 4, Folder 311)
      - No. 5, sermons 14-15, 1739 (Box 4, Folder 312)
      - No. 6, sermons 16-17, 1739 Jun 17 (Box 4, Folder 313)
      - No. 7, sermons 18-19, 1739 (Box 4, Folder 314)
      - No. 8, sermons 20-21, 1739 (Box 4, Folder 315)
      - No. 9, sermons 22-23, 1739 (Box 4, Folder 316)
      - No. 10, sermons 24-25, [1739] (Box 4, Folder 317)
      - No. 11, sermons 26-27, 1739 (Box 4, Folder 318)
      - No. 12, sermons 28-30, 1739 Aug (Box 4, Folder 319)
    - IS. 52:3: "1...We have sold ourselves for nought... 2. Those that come to Christ are redeemed without money" (p. 4), 1740 Nov (Box 4, Folder 320)
    - IS. 52:15: "The suffering of Christ for sinners is a very strange and wonderful thing" (p. 1), 1752 Jul 26
      See: Box 13, folder 997
    - IS. 53:3: "That our Lord Jesus Christ when here upon the earth met with abundance of contempt and reproach" (p. 3) (Box 5, Folder 321)
    - IS. 53:3: "Our Lord Jesus Christ when he dwelt here on the earth was one that was very much used to affliction" (p. 2), 1736-55 (Box 5, Folder 322)
      July 1753, preached to Stockbridge Indians
    - IS. 53:3: Text: "A man of sorrows...", 1753 Jul
      See: Box 13, folder 998
    - IS. 53:7: "The meekness of Jesus Christ was especially manifested in his behavior under his last sufferings" (p. 2), 1753/4 Feb (Box 5, Folder 323)
    - IS. 53:7: "...suffered much from his first coming into the world" (p. 1), 1752 May
      See: Box 13, folder 999
    - IS. 53:7: "1. Most cruelly used... 2. Opened not his mouth..." (p. 1), 1755 Dec (Box 5, Folder 324)
    - IS. 53:10: "That Christ should see sinners converted and saved was part of the reward that God promised to him for his sufferings" (p. 3) (Box 5, Folder 325)
    - IS. 53:10: "Christ in his last sufferings suffered extremely from the hand of God the Father" (p. 1), 1744 May (Box 5, Folder 326)
    - IS. 53:11: "Such delight doth Christ take in the salvation and eternal blessedness of those that he has loved, that he is fully satisfied with it as reward enough for all the suffering he has undergone" (p. 1), 1741/2 Feb (Box 5, Folder 327)
    - IS. 55:1: "Prop I. There is excellent provision made for the refreshment and nourishment of souls in Jesus Christ" (p. 1), 1745, 1757 (Box 5, Folder 328)
    - IS. 55:1-3: "Obs. I. All mankind seek after something to make 'em happy..." (p. 1), 1755 May
      See: Box 13, folder 1000
    - IS. 55:2: "I. Sinners in their pursuits of happiness are at great expense and labor for nothing...", 1746, 1757 (Box 5, Folder 329)
    - IS. 55:3: "The excellency of this covenant and the great desirabless of an interest in its blessings, is set forth here by two things: 1. That it is an everlasting covenant. 2. That the mercies promised in it are sure" (p. 2), 1746 Aug (Box 5, Folder 330)
    - IS. 55:6: "How men should seek and call upon Him" (p. 1), 1755 Aug
      See: Box 13, folder 1001
    - IS. 55:7-9: "Gods thoughts & ways in the exercises of his mercy towards sinful men, are not like theirs but as different from em & as much above 'em as heaven is above the earth" (p. 4), 1745 Jan (Box 5, Folder 331)
    - IS. 55:7-9: "The kindness of God is above all the kindness of men as the heavens are high above the earth" (p. 1), 1752 Nov 16
      See: Box 13, folder 1002
    - IS. 57:15: "I. God is the eternal Being. II. God is the high and lofty One. III. God is he whose name is holy..." (p. 1), 1754 Apr
      See: Box 13, folder 1003
    - IS. 57:21: "First. No peace of sweet and happy agreement. The peace that men are capable of the enjoyment of is of three kinds, neither of which can wicked men have..." (p. 1), 1742, 1753 (Box 5, Folder 332)
      Contains a letter from Rev. Jonathan Judd of Suffield, 1742 Dec 15, relating to his troubles there
    - IS. 58:3-5: "When it is a degenerate time among a people they are ordinarily exceedingly hypocritical in keeping fast days" (p. 4), 1734 Apr (Box 5, Folder 333)
    - IS. 60:19: "What I propose from these words is to shew how the God of Christians is their glory" (p. 1), 1753 Jun (Box 5, Folder 334)
      "Northampton"
    - IS. 61:1: "Christ is come into the world and brings good news for poor distressed souls that are humbled and grieved for their sins" (p. 1), 1753 Oct
      See: Box 13, folder 1004
    - IS. 61:2: "A time of great pouring out of the Spirit is always a time of remarkable favor to some and of extraordinary vengeance on others" (p. 3), 1741 May (Box 5, Folder 335)
    - IS. 62:6-7: "God's professing people ought earnestly and importunately to pray to God that he would accomplish those great things that he has spoken of to bring to pass a glorious state of his church on earth" (p. 3), 1741 Apr (Box 5, Folder 336)
    - IS. 63:8-10: "For a people after solemn covenanting with God and after God has dealt very graciously with them, to turn and rebel against him is the way to have God turn to their enemy and fight against them" (p. 2), 1744 Aug (Box 5, Folder 337)
      "The first quarterly lecture"
    - IS. 64:4: "In Jesus Christ and by the work of redemption new things are provided and accomplished for God's people that are beyond all that ever were seen and heard of or in any respect perceived before by any creature from the beginning of the world" (p. 3), 1748 May (Box 5, Folder 338)
    - IS. 64:5: "To remember God in his ways so as under all dispensations to cleave to him and our duty as placing our happiness therein, is the only way to have God at last meet us in a way of mercy" (p. 1), 1746 Aug (Box 5, Folder 339)
    - IS. 65:13-14: "When the appointed time comes of the saints' great joy, then especially shall be the time of the sinners' wailing..." (p. 1), 1749, 1755 (Box 5, Folder 340)
    - IS. 65:20: "It becomes persons that are advanced in years to be answerably advanced in their attainments in religion" (p. 7), 1738 Dec (Box 5, Folder 341)
    - IS. 66:23-24: "The misery of the damned in hell is one of those great things that the saints in their blessed and joyful state in heaven shall behold and take great notice of throughout all eternity" (p. 1), 1742 Jun (Box 5, Folder 342)
    - JER. 2:5: "When a covenant people that have formerly seemed to cleave to God and manifest an high esteem of him do afterward depart from him, it carries in it a reflection on God as though they had found some iniquity in him" (p. 5), 1738 Apr (Box 5, Folder 343)
    - JER. 2:23: "Persons ought to endeavor to be convinced of sin" (p. 3), 1734/5 Jan (Box 5, Folder 344)
    - JER. 2:31: "The grand contest between God and sinners is who shall be chief" (p. 1), 1748 Aug (Box 5, Folder 345)
      "Baptism, Funeral, Quarterly Lecture"
    - JER. 2:32: "Christ is the ornament and as it were the beautiful attire of true saints" (p. 3), 1737 Jul 20 (Box 5, Folder 346)
    - JER. 5:9: "That tis unreasonable to think that God will take no care to punish the wickedness that there is in the world" (p. 3), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 347)
    - JER. 5:21-22: "Tis a sottish and unreasonable thing for men not to fear God and tremble at his presence" (p. 5), 1738 Mar (Box 5, Folder 348)
    - JER. 5:31: "They that are going on in sin would do well to consider what they shall do in the end thereof" (p. 3) (Box 5, Folder 349)
    - JER. 6:4: "Tis very sorrowful when tis late in the day with persons and a work of great importance and difficult remains undone that must be done before the day be past" (p. 1) (Box 5, Folder 350)
    - JER. 6:29-30: "That it argues great danger of being finally left of God, when sinners have lived long unconverted under eminent means of conversion" (p. 4) (Box 5, Folder 351)
    - JER. 8:7: "They that don't observe and improve their special seasons for the good of their souls are less observant of what is for their own preservation and comfort than the very fowls of the air" (p. 1), 1741 Mar (Box 5, Folder 352)
      "Private meeting at Pascommuck"
    - JER. 8:8: "The Bible is all in vain to them that continue in sin" (p. 1), 1749 Dec (Box 5, Folder 353)
    - JER. 8:11: "Tis greatly to be desired that we should have a thorough and not only a slight and deceitful cure of our spiritual wound" (p. 4), 1733 Oct (Box 5, Folder 354)
    - JER. 10:16: "Doc. 1. God is his people's portion" (p. 3) "Doc. 2 God's people are God's portion" (p. 17), two sermons, 1757, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 355)
    - JER. 13:27: "Many sinners have means often used for their conversion and after pretend to do something towards it and yet it never once comes to pass" (p. 3), 1748, 1757 (Box 5, Folder 356)
    - JER. 17:5-6: "They that trust in the creature will be left in an utterly destitute and hopeless condition and shall not see when good comes" (p. 4) (Box 5, Folder 357)
    - JER. 17:5-6: "The way of trusting in man is the way not to have God's blessing but his curse" (p. 1), 1749/50 Jan (Box 5, Folder 358)
    - JER. 17:7-8: "They that trust in God have a full foundation of good to live upon that won't fail in evil and calamitous times" (p. 3) (Box 5, Folder 359)
    - JER. 17:9: "The heart of man is exceeding deceitful" (p. 2), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 360)
    - JER. 23:29: "Prop. I. The hearts of the children of men are naturally like a rock. 2. That the word of God subdues and dissolves the rocky hearts of the children of men. 3. That herein it is like a fire and a hammer" (p. 1), 1749 Apr (Box 5, Folder 361)
    - JER. 29:13: "When those that have forsaken God are come to seek him so as to search for him with all their hearts they are in the way to find him" (p. 1), 1742 Apr (Box 5, Folder 362)
    - JER. 31:3: "The love wherewith God has loved his saints is an everlasting love" (p. 3), 1736 Mar (Box 5, Folder 363)
    - JER. 36:6-7: "1. The business of a fast day is not only to offer what we have to say to God in prayer but to hearken [to] what he says to us in his word. 2. Whatever any man may do outwardly...then only do men really present their supplications...when they are convinced of sin and brought to repentance..." (p. 2), 1748, 1757 (Box 5, Folder 364)
    - JER. 42:20: "That there are some men do nothing but dissemble in their pretences of disposedness to their duty" (p. 5) (Box 5, Folder 365)
      A sacrament sermon
    - JER. 44:4: "Sin is exceeding hateful to God" (p. 3), 1744, 1754 (Box 5, Folder 366)
      Preached to Stockbridge Indians, 1754
    - JER. 44:26: "Sometimes when God has used many means with men to bring them to forsake their sins and they will not forsake them, God doth as it were swear in wrath that they never shall forsake them" (p. 5), 1734 Jul (Box 5, Folder 367)
    - JER. 50:4-5: "Prop. I. There is encouragement for such to seek God as have been far from him and under tokens of his anger" (p. 2), 1749 Aug (Box 5, Folder 368)
    - JER. 50:6: "Christ is as [it] were the resting place of his people" (p. 1), 1755 Jun
      See: Box 13, folder 1005
    - JER. 51:5: "The mercy of God towards a professing people is very wonderful when he don't forsake them though their land be filled with sin against him" (p. 2), 1745, 1757 (Box 5, Folder 369)
      Thanksgiving sermon (1745)
    - EZEK. 3:27: "That when God sends his messengers to preach his word, his word shall not be in vain, or God shall not be frustrated, whether men hear or whether they forbear" (p. 3) (Box 5, Folder 370)
    - EZEK. 7:16: "That at a time when a people are called to a general humiliation it becomes each one to mourn for his own iniquity" (p. 4), n.d.
      See: Box 13, folders 1006-1007
      "For a day of public humiliation"
    - EZEK. 8:8: "When God comes to execute deserved punishment on ungodly men he will not pity them" (p. 3), 1738 Jun (Box 5, Folder 371)
    - EZEK. 15:2-4: "Mankind, if they bring forth no fruit to God are wholly useless unless it be in their destruction", 1734 Jul (Box 5, Folder 372)
    - EZEK. 16:5-6: "Man never would have had any pity from anyone in the miserable state into which he fell, if God had not pitied him" (p. 3), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 373)
    - EZEK. 16:63: "God's people ought to be much in reflecting on their sins and humbling themselves for them after they have evidences of God's having forgiven them" (p. 4), 1735/6 Jan (Box 5, Folder 374)
    - EZEK. 18:30-32: "I. God will judge all men according to their ways" (p. 1), 1754 Jun
      See: Box 13, folder 1008
    - EZEK. 19:12: "When God by death removes from a people those in place of public authority and rule that have been as strong rods, tis an awful judgment of God on that people, and worthy of great lamentation" (p. 5), 1748 Jun (Box 5, Folder 375)
      "On occasion of the death of Col Stoddard, June 1748"